Gaither mss., LMC 2215
Lilly Library
Gaither mss.
1955-1986
Lilly Library
Gaither, Mary E.
LMC 2215
1 Box 1 standard
The Gaither mss., 1955-1986 consists of correspondence and writings of Mary Elizabeth Gaither (1917-2018) relating primarily to work on Leonard and Virginia Woolf and on the publications of their Hogarth Press. Additions to the collection include receipts and invoices, 1961-1969, for the purchase of Hogarth Press books.
Access Restrictions
This collection is open for research.
Many collections are housed offsite; retrieval requires advance notice. Please make an appointment a minimum of one week in advance of your visit.
Biographical Note
The Gaither mss., 1955-1986 contains the correspondence and writings of Indiana University Professor Emeritus Mary Elizabeth Gaither (1917-2018). Born in Alton, Indiana, Gaither moved to Louisville, Kentucky as a young girl with her parents, where she attended the public school system and later the University of Louisville. For a brief five-year period, Gaither taught high school English there before she decided to enlist in the WAVES: the women's branch of the United States Naval Reserve. Between 1943 and 1946, she became an ensign and lieutenant and later worked at the Pentagon as a control officer. After World War II, she returned to teaching English. At the University of Louisville, she served as an instructor and also completed her master's degree in English literature. At Indiana University, she continued to teach English and received her doctorate in comparative literature. She focused, as the collection's writings reveal, on Virginia Woolf and other twentieth-century British writers. Before her retirement in 1982, she also served as the director of Children's Literature and as an Associate Dean of the Graduate School.
Scope and Content Note
Consists of correspondence and writings of Mary Elizabeth Gaither relating primarily to work on Leonard and Virginia Woolf and on the publications of their Hogarth Press. Additions to the collection include receipts and invoices, 1961-1969, for the purchase of Hogarth Press books.
The first folder of correspondence is between Leonard Woolf and Mary E. Gaither, 1955-1961. In 1961 Gaither interviewed Woolf and the notes for that interview are in the first folder of writings. The majority of the correspondence is from 1974-1986 and is primarily with book dealer and bibliogra­pher J. Howard Woolmer, first of Andes, New York, later of Revere, Pennsylvania. In 1976, Woolmer's A Checklist of the Hogarth Press, with a Short History of the Press by Mary E. Gaither, was published by the Hogarth Press in London and by Woolmer-Brotherton in the US. Work on the revised edition began in 1985 and was published in late 1986. In addition to "the Short History" present in the writings section, there are offprints of two articles that Gaither did for The Dictionary of Literary Biography, vol. 112, in 1991: "Hogarth Press" and "Nonesuch Press."
A few miscellaneous items at the end of the collection include a photographic copy of a portrait of Leonard Woolf that is in the National Portrait Gallery, and a group of news clippings about him, mostly from the 1960s.
Additions to the Gaither mss. include receipts and invoices, 1961-1969, for the purchase of Hogarth Press books by Mary Gaither. Her main source for her collection was British bookseller R.A. Brimmell, first located in Middlesex then in Sussex. Also present in this group is an exchange with American bookseller Robert A. Wilson relating to the purchase of Virginia Woolf's Two Stories in 1965.
Acquisition Information
Gift, 1999, 2001.
Publishers and publishing; English literature; Modernism (art); English prose literature--20th century--History and criticism; Literature, Modern--20th century--History and criticism--Theory, etc; English literature--20th century--Biography; Indiana University; Hogarth Press.; Gaither, Mary E.; Woolf, Leonard, 1880-1969 --Correspondence.; Woolf, Leonard, 1880-1969.; Woolmer, J. Howard.
- Collection, 1955-1986
  - Correspondence with Leonard Woolf, 1955-1961 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence – general, 1965-1974 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence re: Hogarth checklist and history, chiefly with J. Howard Woolmer, 1974-1986 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Writings: interview with Leonard Woolf, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Writings, re: Hogarth Press manuscript, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Hogarth Press Bibliography, draft, ca. 1968 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - [Short history of Hogarth Press], and Appendix, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Offprints: review of Hogarth Press checklist; "Hogarth Press" from DLB 112; "Nonesuch Press" from DLB 112 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Notes, pencil, re: Lytton Strachey / Virginia Woolf correspondence (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Photograph of portrait of Leonard Woolf (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Miscellaneous clippings and printed items. (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Receipts and invoices, for purchase of Hogarth Press books., 1961-1964 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Receipts and invoices, 1965-1969 (Box 1, Folder 13)